Hi everybody, I'm Jim Rohn.
What a pleasure it is for me to come and
visit with you for just a few minutes here today,
tell you briefly a little bit about my
story, and share some ideas that might be beneficial.
I've lectured in some high school classrooms in
California and Arizona and some universities and colleges,
Pepperdine University, San Diego
State, Arizona State University,
and so I've had a chance to talk to kids
that are interested in themselves and interested in their future,
interested in America, interested in what
they can do with their lives,
and listening to stories that might be beneficial.
And I don't have a chance to, you know,
visit all of the schools and universities around the world,
so this is a great chance for me, by
video, to have a chance to tell you my story.
Just briefly, let me tell you my
story. I grew up in Idaho, farm country.
My father still lives on the old
homestead where I grew up, southwestern Idaho.
He'll be 91 his next birthday,
and I'm very proud of him.
I went to high school. I graduated.
I went to college one year.
Halfway through my second year, I decided
I was smart enough, so I quit.
One of my major mistakes.
I should have stayed in school.
But I thought, you know, heck,
I'm smart enough to get a job.
And back then I thought, you know, that was it. If
you're smart enough to get a job, what else would you need?
Found out later, a big mistake.
But anyway, I quit school at age 19, went to work.
A little while later, persuaded a beautiful young lady to marry me
with a lot of fancy promises.
And fortunately for me, we got married.
Little while later, I started my family and I'm out
there working hard, doing the best I thought I could.
But year by year, I
kept falling a little further behind.
You know, buying a little more than
I could conveniently pay for on time.
And the creditors are finally starting to call saying,
hey, you told us the check was in the mail.
I'm not feeling at all good about that.
About age 25, I've got pennies in my pocket.
I've got nothing in the bank and way behind on my big mouth promises
to my family and wondering what could I do to make my life better?
I was willing to work hard.
That was not my problem, but I just
wasn't making the progress I wanted to make.
And then good fortune came my way.
Sometimes it's difficult to describe good fortune.
Why something remarkable happens to you at a point.
At a particular time.
One of my friends says,
well, hey, things don't just happen.
Things happen just.
And maybe that's it.
I don't know.
But my good fortune was I had
a chance to meet a very wealthy man.
His name was Mr. Shouf, Mr. Shouf.
A friend of mine had gone to work for
him and he started telling me about this man.
He said, you've got to meet this man.
He's rich, but he's easy to talk to.
And he's got a remarkable philosophy of life.
And he kept going on.
And I thought, well, I've got to meet this man.
So shortly after that, I had
a chance to meet this Mr. Shouf.
And I was impressed.
He was rich.
He was easy to talk to.
Within a few minutes, I was dazzled.
And I said to myself, I would
give anything if I could be like that.
Rich and easy to talk to.
What would it take?
And then I thought, if I could just get around somebody like him
and if he would teach me and coach me, I would do it all.
And that was my good fortune.
A few months later.
This wealthy man, Mr. Shouf, hired
me and gave me a job.
And I went to work for him.
And I spent the next five years in his employ.
And then, unfortunately, at age 49, he died.
But I got to spend five years with this remarkable man, his last
five years of his life and the first five years of my new life.
And my dream came true during that five year period.
This man took the time
to teach me and coach me.
He taught me the books to read.
He taught me the disciplines
and he taught me the skills.
And he taught me the changes
to make in my language and personality.
And the things he shared with me during that five years changed
my whole life, changed my income, changed my bank account, changed my future.
I've never been the same.
By the time I was 31
years old, I was a millionaire.
So he taught me economics as well.
So how lucky can you
get to meet the right person?
At the right time?
Who takes the time to share with
you ideas that can change your life?
A lot of rich people, right?
Don't take the time.
But he did.
And he also had the ability.
Some people want to share their experiences, but
they don't quite know how to say it.
But he had it all.
And he used language that I could understand.
And those ideas greatly affected my life.
I wish he was still alive today.
If he was, I'd be calling
him today one more time thanking him.
For the time he spent with me sharing his
life and his experiences that so dramatically affected my life.
Then how I really came to
be invited to speak to you today.
30 plus years ago, I
was living in Beverly Hills, California.
And a friend of mine one day said, Jim, you've
got to come and tell your story to my service club.
He belonged to the Rotary Club.
And he said, I know your story.
Idaho farm boy makes it to Beverly Hills.
But he said, I know my club
members would love to hear your story.
Would you come and and at
our breakfast meeting and tell your story?
And I said, OK.
So I arranged a little talk,
went and shared my story that morning.
And guess what?
They liked it.
And my phone rang.
Another club called and said, would
you come and tell us that story?
My phone rings.
Another club calls.
So we've heard about your story.
We have a luncheon meeting.
Would you come share your story?
First thing I know, I'm spending a little piece
of my time giving these breakfast talks and luncheon talks.
And then one day a man who heard my talk about three
times said, would you come and talk to my management and salespeople?
He said, I've got this little company going.
And if you he said, if you would spend some time
talking with my management and salespeople, I'd be happy to pay you.
And I thought, wow, wouldn't that be something?
Tell my story and my experiences and get paid.
He said, I'd be happy to.
Little did I know that was the beginning.
Of a whole new.
Brand new adventure.
For me.
And sharing my story and speeches
and talks and seminars and lectures.
And now this business become one of my
most flourishing enterprises takes me around the world.
I went to many countries just this year,
had my largest audience early this year in Spain.
12,000 people.
10 different languages being translated at the same time.
The whole audience with the earphones on.
It's interesting when you lecture with.
Multi languages.
You know, when you hit the punch line, you know,
the Spanish laugh first and then the French get it.
And then finally the Italians get it.
And last, the Germans finally get it.
And then I say, hey, the Germans finally got it.
I guess we can continue.
You know, some languages take long
longer to translate than other languages.
But what an exciting adventure for me.
I was in Israel this year.
I lectured in France.
My first trip to Prague, Czechoslovakia.
Lisbon, Portugal.
Last year I was in London lecturing.
Happened to be there the same
night Pavarotti was singing in London.
So, big dilemma for the people in London.
Shall we go see Jim Rohn
or shall we go listen to Pavarotti?
Well, I must admit he
had more people than I did.
Like 150,000 more.
He did a free concert in Hyde Park.
And they expected a quarter of a million.
But only 150,000 showed up because it rained.
And they all got soaked from Prince Charles on down.
But they sat in the rain and listened to Pavarotti.
I would have been happy that evening, right, to cancel my
seminar and go sit in the rain and listen to Pavarotti.
Anyway, he and I have agreed now not to
appear in the same city on the same day anymore.
Not really.
But how exciting for me to be able to
travel all around the world and share my story.
And then especially to have this chance
today to come and visit with you.
Thank you.
And when I get a chance to speak at a high
school class or a university class, I'm always excited about it.
I'm limited in time.
So I wanted to use this way to come and share my story with you and some ideas
that might be helpful in your career for the future, in your now busy life as a student.
And then wherever you find yourself in the years to
come, some of the things I'm going to share with you.
I want you to remember for a long, long time because
the ideas I want to translate for you drastically affected my life.
And if I can share now and affect your life and you write me a letter or
tell me in person someday, Mr. Rohn, I listened to your video and I watched it carefully.
And sure enough, some of the
ideas that you shared greatly affected me.
And here's what's happened to my bank account.
Here's what happened to me in school.
Here's what's happening to my future.
That'll give me great, great satisfaction.
So the man who shared my story.
Thank you.
He shared with me ideas that changed my life.
I want to share with
you three of those basic subjects.
When I met him, I was 25 years old.
And when I first got acquainted with him, I used
a lot of excuses as to why I wasn't doing well.
And he said, well, tell me
a little bit about your story.
And I told him, you know, I was behind on
my bills, had pennies in my pocket, nothing in the bank.
But I was embarrassed about being behind
on my big mouth promises to my family.
And then he gave me one little
simple phrase that really forever changed my life.
And here's what he said.
Mr. Rohn, if you want the future
to change for you, you've got to change.
And he said, if you don't change, the next six years
of your life is going to be just like the last six.
You'll still be behind on your bills.
You'll still be behind on your promises.
But then he gave it to
me in the form of a promise.
When I was 25 years old,
I've remembered it all these years.
And I've shared this promise.
And I've shared this promise now with probably over
three million people in the last 30 plus years.
And it's going to be valid for you.
So listen carefully to this promise.
My teacher said to me, young man, if
you will change, everything will change for you.
If you will get better,
everything will get better for you.
What a clear message that was for me.
He said, if you'll change
your philosophy, you'll change your habits.
If you'll refine your thinking.
If you'll change and accept some new disciplines.
If you'll turn the corner where you've been in
the past, go for a new life for the future.
He said, all kinds of remarkable things
will happen for you if you will change.
Before I met Mr. Shouff, I used to cross
my fingers and say, I sure hope things will change.
I was hoping the government would change and the tax structure would
change and that my boss would change and pay me more money.
I was hoping that, you know, economics would change.
And prices would come down.
And I was hoping that circumstances would get better.
And then I discovered from my teacher that
those things are going to continue the same.
In fact, all of those things that happen to
us is kind of like the wind that blows.
And the wind blows on us all.
In fact, in America, especially, the last six
and a half thousand years of recorded history,
we've got probably the most famous story.
The most favorable wind that's ever blown.
Economics and circumstances, living in a free
country, democracy and freedom, an excellent economy.
Sure, we struggle at times.
But compared to the rest of the world in the last
six and a half thousand years, we've got the best wind ever.
But if you just let the wind blow, I'm telling
you, it won't take you where you want to go.
All of us must use this wind to take us
to the dreams we've got, to the equities we want,
to the money we want, to the income we want,
and to all the things we want our life to have.
This is where we want to go.
And we've got a good wind, but we must not
leave our future just to the wind, just to the economy,
just to the structure of
the way things are happening today.
Here's what we must learn to do,
and that is set a good sail.
And if you'll learn to set a good sail, and
that's what my teacher taught me in those early days.
He said, Mr. Rohn, the wind is going to blow.
It's going to blow however it's going to blow.
Politics are going to be politics, and
the economy is going to be the economy.
And however it turns out, that's
the way it's going to be.
What you must learn to do is
not to wish for a better wind.
That's naive.
The key is to wish for the wisdom and the skills
and the learning so that you can set a better sail.
And so that's what I did at age 25.
I went to work not on the economy.
I went to work not on the community.
I didn't go to work
to try to change the government.
I didn't go to work to try
to change my boss or the company.
I didn't go to work to try to change circumstances.
I went to work to try to change myself.
And I picked up that
promise my teacher shared with me.
That if I would change, my income would change.
If I would change, my bank account would change.
If I would change, my future would change.
And sure enough, his promise came true for me.
The first six years of my
economic life, I wound up broke.
Those pennies in my pocket, nothing
in the bank, behind on my promises.
The second six years of my
economic life, I wound up rich.
But interestingly enough, the second six years of my economic life, the
government was about the same and the economy was about the same.
You know, the companies were about the same.
What they paid was the same.
Circumstances around me were the same.
You know, my negative relatives were the same.
But I was not the same.
That's how my life changed.
That's how things changed.
Things started working for me, changing
my life all those years ago.
So that's what I wanted to
share with you to begin with.
This beginning of what Mr. Shove shared with me that if I wanted
my life to change, this was what I was going to have to do.
And so he broke it down into three subjects that really made
an impact on my life and I want to share those with you.
The first subject he called personal development.
And the second subject he called setting goals.
And the third was how to become financially independent.
And I'd like to give you just a few clues
from those three major subjects that so dramatically affected my life.
And let's get started.
The first one is personal development.
Now in illustrating personal development,
Mr. Shove, my teacher, said,
Mr. Shove, my teacher, started with money.
You know, money's not the only
place to start in talking personal development.
But it's where he started, so let me
share the thoughts he shared with me back then.
Let me share them with you.
Here's the best lesson I can give you on economics.
It's very simple.
We get paid for bringing value to the marketplace.
That's about as simple as that.
It's as simple as I can put economics.
We get paid for bringing value to the marketplace.
Now, it takes time to bring value to the marketplace.
However, we do not get paid for time.
So we cross that out.
Mistakenly, the man says, I'm
making about $20 for an hour.
Not true.
If that was true, you could just stay home, right?
And have them send your money.
So that's not true.
We don't get paid for time.
We get paid for value brought to the marketplace.
Now, since that's true, here's one of the
key questions of my talk to you today.
Is it possible to become twice as valuable to the
marketplace and make twice as much money in the same time?
Is that possible?
The answer is yes.
Could you become three times as valuable as you might be right now
to the marketplace and make three times as much money in the same time?
And the answer is yes.
Five times?
Ten times?
Of course.
America is unique.
It's a ladder decline.
It starts down here, let's say, at
$5 an hour and it keeps going up.
Top income last year, $80 million.
The guy who runs Coca-Cola.
Now, that's a heck of a ladder.
That's why everybody wants to come here, right?
The boat people are not headed for Vietnam.
People haven't plotted and schemed for 50 years saying if
I could just get to Poland, everything would be fine.
Not true.
Everybody wants to come to America.
And the reason is because we've got
the best wind ever blowing in our favor.
We've got the best economic opportunity anybody's
had in six and a half thousand years.
And all you have to do is
understand it and take advantage of it.
Now, there's some key questions to ask here.
Why would the marketplace pay someone only $5 an hour?
Very simple answer.
They're not very valuable.
They're not very valuable to the marketplace.
Now, we must underline to the marketplace.
This person might be a very valuable brother.
Yes.
Member of the family valuable.
Valuable member of the church.
Of course.
Valuable citizen of the country.
Yes.
Valuable in the sight of God.
No doubt.
We're all of equal value in the sight of God.
But if you're not very valuable to
the marketplace, you don't get much money.
You say, well, it shouldn't be that.
Well, then you got to start your own country.
You know, this one's been in process for 200 years, and this
is the best we've been able to come up with so far.
But here's the key.
You don't have to stay here.
Now, there was a big debate in Congress
last year that this $5 was not enough.
Should be six.
But we don't need legislation.
Six is already on this ladder.
The next step up.
You know, if you work for McDonald's, they'll pay
you $5 an hour to take out the trash.
If you whistle while you take out
the trash, they'll pay you $6 an hour.
So we don't need that legislation.
You just need to take lessons on how to whistle.
Have a good attitude.
Now, as you begin to climb this ladder, why
would the marketplace pay some people $50 an hour?
Answer, evidently, they must be
more valuable to the marketplace.
Ten times more valuable.
And is that possible for someone
to be ten times more valuable?
Men earn $50 an hour instead of five?
And the answer is yes.
That's what America is all about.
Now, why would the marketplace
pay some people $500 an hour?
Evidently, this person must be
much more valuable to the marketplace.
That's what's important to understand, to the marketplace.
And would the marketplace pay one
person $80 million for one year's work?
And the answer is, of course.
If you helped a company make a
billion dollars, would they pay you $80 million?
I'm telling you, it is possible.
And that's why America is so exciting.
That's why this financial ladder is so exciting.
It's possible for all of this to come true
for all of you, no matter where you start.
As a student in school, just getting started out
there in the workplace, this is all possible for you.
Now, Mr. Shouff gave me the
clue on how to climb this ladder.
I climbed this ladder as
high as I wanted to climb.
Now, we're talking primarily economics here.
There's a lot of other ways to become valuable to your family,
valuable to your friends, valuable to the community, valuable to the team, right?
Valuable to the team effort, valuable to the concert.
But here's what he said to me.
In climbing this ladder economically, all you have to do
is work harder on yourself than you do on your job.
Once I heard that, it made sense to me.
I kept hoping that everything else would change around me.
Found out that if I went to work on myself, worked on my
skills, worked on my language, if I became better than I was each year,
if I grew in skills and language and vocabulary
and competence, then I would become attractive to the marketplace.
Not very long ago, a company called me and said,
Mr. Rohn, we're expanding into the market.
We're expanding internationally.
We'd like to have a bit
of your expertise to help us.
Would you give us a bit of your time?
We'll add some millions to your fortune.
And I said, okay.
And I thought later, isn't that interesting?
They would call me.
Then my second thought was, of course they'd call me.
Who else would they call?
I can get the job done.
Now, what a contrast for me, farm boy from Idaho, raised
in obscurity, parents of modest means, broke when I was 25.
How come I would get a telephone call?
Why would someone offer me a lot of
money to help them in expanding around the world?
Simple answer, evidently, something happened to me
between age 25 and where I am today.
And I can tell you where it all started.
From my teacher, Mr. Shouff, who said to me,
we don't have to change what's going on out there.
That's the wind that's blowing.
All we have to do is
change what's going on in here.
And now there are several ways
to do that on personal development.
And let me give you those ways.
Here's the first one.
We must learn from personal experience.
Pretty simple.
Learn from what happens to you.
Take a look back over the last few months.
Did you make some mistakes?
How could you correct those for the future?
Take a look back over the last year.
Have you done it right or done it wrong?
Let's correct it for the next year.
Learn from your personal experience.
Mr. Shouff asked me when I first met him.
He said, Mr. Owen, how are you doing?
You've been out there now six years.
And I said, I'm not doing very well.
He said, I suggest you not do that anymore.
What a simple, swift analysis to my situation.
He said, if you keep doing it, the
next six years will be like the last six.
You don't want that to happen.
Let's make the changes.
So learn from your personal experience.
Now here's number two, why I came
to share this video experience with you today.
And that, I call it OPE.
Other people's experiences.
That's me.
Other people.
That's your teacher.
That's your friends and colleagues.
Other people.
The people you meet that can
pass along to you their experiences.
What's happened to them, the mistakes they made, how they corrected them, how they changed
their health and changed their bank account and changed their income and changed their future.
That's it.
Other people.
Now there's two kinds of people to learn from.
One is failures.
It's too bad failures don't give success.
Failures don't give seminars, right?
That would be valuable.
Bring your notebook.
Have them tell you how they lost it all and threw it all away,
threw their health away and threw their friendships away and things didn't work out well.
That would be valuable.
But now then we must also learn
from positive people that have done well.
They've got the health and so we
ask them, how did you become so healthy?
They've got the skills so we ask
them, how did you become this skillful?
They've got the income so we ask them, how did
you get here in such a short period of time?
So now here's what's important in personal development.
In learning from other people,
we learn number one by observation.
We learn what we see.
We watch people that are successful in what they do.
In sports, we watch their disciplines.
In business, we watch their disciplines.
By observation, what we can see.
The reason I created this video is something
that you could see someone's experiences translated for you.
Second, we learn by what we hear.
I've got some of my lectures on cassette tapes so
you know you can take them with you wherever you go.
And learn by listening.
Turn your car into a mobile classroom and listen.
And then listen to the sermon on Sunday morning.
Listen to the lectures.
Listen to the teacher.
Listen to someone who's got something good to say.
And then number three is
vitally important on personal development.
And that is read all the books.
All the books you can possibly read in your lifetime.
Mr. Shoff got me started on my library.
I've got one of the better libraries.
Haven't read everything in it but
I feel smarter just walking in it.
My library.
At least I was smart enough to buy it.
Now I've got to be smart enough to read it.
Then of course I've got to be smart
enough to decide what's valuable and then do it.
But this one is very important.
Become a good reader.
Some books that helped change my life.
Mr. Shoff recommended them.
He recommended of course the Bible.
And my parents made sure I was a
pretty good scholar by the time I was 18.
That's been so beneficial for me.
Drawing from those illustrations.
Reading about those stories.
People who made it and people who didn't make it.
And what the difference was.
And then other books that
helped to really change my life.
One called Think and Grow Rich by Napoleon Hill.
And then a book that helped me become
financially independent by the time I was 31.
And that book is called
The Richest Man in Babylon by George Clayson.
And I'm going to share a little bit of that
book with you when I get to financial independence today.
Our third subject.
But I started reading the books.
Attending the classes.
Making sure that I got in front
of people that had something good to say.
And then I started keeping a journal.
One of the major things my teacher
taught me was to keep a journal.
He said don't trust your memory.
If you hear something good just make a little note.
And write it down.
Now at first I took notes on pieces of paper.
And torn off corners and backs of old envelopes.
And it didn't serve me well.
You know thrown in a drawer.
Then I learned to keep a journal.
A bound copy of all my notes.
So I would suggest you do the same.
Things that impress you.
A poem that impresses you.
When you attend a class.
Some of the ideas that impressed you.
Jot them down.
You read something in a magazine.
Right?
Some ideas.
Take those out.
Put them in your journal.
Keep a good journal the rest of your life.
This will serve you well.
My journals make up a
significant portion of my own library.
And if you saw my library and saw my journals.
I tell you what you'd have to say.
This is the library.
And these are the journals of a very serious student.
No wonder Mr. Rohn is invited to lecture
and speak on his experiences around the world.
So I want the same thing to happen to you.
Value captured.
That you can resort to later.
And then go back over it and review it.
And let it become valuable to you.
So that's my first subject.
Personal development.
Work harder on yourself than you do on your job.
Develop the skills.
Learn the lessons.
Take the classes.
Absorb all that is being taught to you these days.
And then later on of
course you can sort it out.
What's valuable to you.
And how to refine it.
For your business and for
your life and for your future.
But the main thing is to get it.
And start this process of personal change.
Personal development.
And let me say it one more time.
If you will change.
Everything will change for you.
You'll never be the same.
You'll keep growing.
As you look back on a few months.
Look back on a few years.
You won't believe the progress you can make.
Economically.
Your relationship with your family.
Your friends.
And whether you're in sports or economics or whatever.
I'm telling you.
That whole process of committing yourself.
For personal change.
Personal value.
Can really make your life.
Unique and worthwhile.
Now let's cover the second subject.
On setting goals.
Mr. Shoff gave me some tips on setting goals.
That changed my life forever.
And I want to share those with you.
So let's talk about setting goals.
And I also want to tie it.
To personal development.
And you'll see how I'm going to do it.
As I progress here.
Setting goals.
We need to take a look into the future.
There are four things.
To consider in terms of attitude.
One is how you feel about the past.
Best advice I can give you on that.
Is treat the past as a school.
Let it teach you.
The mistakes you've made.
The things that went wrong.
The things that didn't work.
Don't use the past as a burden to carry.
And don't use the past as a club.
To beat yourself to death.
Past losses.
Past failures.
Past mistakes.
But let the past be a school.
Tough school maybe.
We've all been through some tough stuff.
So if you feel good about the past.
Draw from it for experience.
And let it teach you.
Then next is how you feel about the future.
We've got to have the future well designed.
The future is called the promise.
And here's what we teach in our leadership series.
The promise of the future can be an awesome force.
For your own future.
The promise of the future.
Designing the future.
There's two ways to face the future.
One is with apprehension.
And the other is with anticipation.
I promise you in my travels around the world.
Most people face the future with apprehension.
And here's why.
They don't have it well designed.
They've sort of left that
up to someone else to fix.
But here's the best way to face the future.
With anticipation.
And you can face the future with anticipation.
If.
The future is clear.
If the future is well designed.
And I would like to have you consider some thoughts with me that help
me to really change my future by giving it some thought and some consideration.
And here it is.
In setting goals it's very simple.
Number one, decide what you want.
You just take a little time.
You sit down and say what do I want?
What kind of skills do I want?
What kind of income do I want for the future?
What would I like?
Where would I like to go?
Places I'd like to visit?
Habits I'd like to acquire?
Skills I'd like to have?
You just take a little time
to think about what you want.
Economics?
Friendships?
People you'd like to meet?
Places you'd like to go?
You just take some time.
And then I suggest when you've thought about
what you want for the future, make a list.
Just jot it all down.
It's really a very simple thing.
It's a very simple process.
And then here's number three.
Keep all the old lists.
I'm telling you this served me so well.
Keeping my old list of goals.
I look back now 10, 20 years ago at goals I set, lists
I made, and I smile now because here's what I thought was so important.
You know, 20 years ago.
Now some of those things aren't even on my list.
I've got a new list.
I've grown.
I've changed.
I've matured.
I've grown to be a good
person, and I'll never forget that.
So if you want number two, write it down.
Number three, keep the old list.
And then here's number four.
When you get something that's on
one of these lists, check it off.
Part of the fun of having
a list is checking it off.
And then if you can add some drama
to checking it off, see, that's what really helps.
I set a goal to go
to Spain many, many years ago.
And when I finally made my first trip to Spain, I
had that journal with me that had that list in it.
And while I had my journal on my lap, waiting
for the wheel, I went out and found a little copy.
And there I was having
dinner, and I could feel the
time it took for just a single person in the room to
read a book, or even write a book, or something like that.
my journal on my lap waiting for the wheels
to touch down in Madrid. I waited until the wheels
touched the runway and I checked it off, just
adding a little drama. So part of the fun of
having a list is checking it off. Now
here's what's important about the list and designing
your future. If the future gets clear, the price
gets easier because you got to remember for every
promise, there's a price to pay. Everybody's got to
pay the price. Everybody's got to do the deal.
Everybody's got to do the disciplines. Everybody
has to pay. But here's what I've discovered.
If the promise is clear and powerful, the price
is easy to pay. The price is some classes. The
price is a few books. The price is
a few disciplines. The price is finding something
that'll make your life better, make you
grow, make you change, make you develop.
So the first thing I want to do is I want to
make sure that I'm not just a book. I'm not just a book.
The first part of the key is to design the
promise. Then what is the price to pay? I'm telling you,
the price will be easy. Anybody in my audience can
pay it, no matter where you are, where you come
from. Color doesn't matter. Religion doesn't
matter. Where you grew up doesn't matter.
Circumstances don't matter. I'm telling you, if you'll
make the promise of the future clear for
yourself, the things you want, the places you want to
go, the things you want to have, the person you
want to become, the skills you want, the homes
you want, the future you want, the friends you want,
all of the values of life that you could
possibly want. If you'll make that clear, make those lists
and be serious about it. I promise you it's an
easy price to pay. Anybody can pay it. And the
best advice I can give you is if I can do
it, you can do it. Farm boy from Idaho raised in obscurity.
I changed my life, turned it upside down,
turned it all around, found economics, found future,
found promise. And if I can do it,
you can do it. So start setting your goals.
And see if you can't get a better excitement
going for the things you want to accomplish for the
future. Now here's my third subject, and
that's called financial independence. Oh, by the way,
before I get to financial independence, let me cover
one more point. One of the major reasons for
setting goals is for what they make of you
in achieving them. My teacher advised me when I first
got started at age 25. He said, Jim,
why don't you set a goal to become a
millionaire? He said, it's got a nice ring to it.
You know, enough zeros to impress your accountant.
And he said, I'm here to help you.
You're only 25 years old. You've been to
one year of college. You've got a beautiful family,
every reason to do it. Why don't you set a
goal to become a millionaire? And he said, here's why.
And I thought he doesn't need to teach me
why. Wouldn't it be nice to have a million dollars?
He said, no, then you'll miss it.
He said, here's why. For what it will make
of you to achieve it. I'm telling you that statement
changed my life. Set the kind of goals
that will make something of you to achieve them.
He said, now, once you become a millionaire,
what's important is not the money. I thought
that's kind of strange teaching. He said, honest,
it isn't important. He said, you could just give
the money away. Now I did better than that. I lost
it all. By the time I was 31, I was a millionaire.
By the time I was 33, I was broke.
And I'll tell you a little bit about that story
later. But when I lost all my money, guess what?
I found out Mr. Shouf was right. What was valuable
was not the money. What was valuable was what I
became to earn the money. The skills I
had, the knowledge I had about the marketplace,
the values that I had going for
me, they were more valuable than the money.
And here's an important statement to remember. It's
not what you get that makes you valuable.
It's what you become.
So part of the key here is to set
the kind of goals that will make you a millionaire.
Don't set them too low so that you don't have to grow and you don't
have to read and you don't have to try and you don't have to stretch.
Don't set them too low. And then don't sell out. Don't go for something that's
going to cost you your virtue or cost you your values or sell out your principles.
There's a good middle road here to follow. Goals that will inspire, goals
that will help you grow, change, develop and become better than you are.
Okay.
Now let's talk about financial independence.
How to become rich by 40, 35 if you're extra
bright, much sooner if you find an opportunity like I did.
Let me show you how I did it.
Financial independence.
First of all,
I like the phrase financial independence.
Some people are a little bit
concerned about using the word becoming rich.
Or becoming wealthy.
And I can understand that.
I struggled a little bit with this.
Is it okay to go for
becoming rich, go for becoming wealthy?
And maybe that's a bit too
strong a word or strong a term.
So here's what I've come up with
that I think is comfortable for me.
And that is how to become financially independent.
I think it's every person's heritage here,
especially in America, to become financially independent.
Now, let me give you
my definition of financial independence.
Financial independence is the ability to live
from the income of your own personal resources.
Financial independence.
Now it depends on how you want to live.
If you need two, three thousand dollars a month, if you need
four or five thousand a month, if you need ten thousand a month.
Some people may need, you
know, a hundred thousand a month.
But whatever you would need to live and you could
earn that living from the income of your own personal resources.
That's what I call financial freedom.
Financial independence.
And let me show you how to acquire it.
If you start at age fifteen, between
ages fifteen and thirty-five is twenty years.
And in my personal opinion, based on my own studies and my own
experience, twenty years, in my opinion, is enough time to become financially independent.
If you're not, you don't live in the wrong country.
Probably what's happened is you have the wrong plan.
And it's easy to be wrong.
It's easy to be a
nice person with the wrong plan.
I found that when I was twenty-five years old.
I was broke at age twenty-five
and I was a nice guy.
You would have liked me.
But I'm telling you, my plans up until
then, especially my financial plan, left me broke.
I totally changed it the next
six years and I became financially independent.
So I know what I'm talking about.
It is possible in a reasonable amount of time.
Fifteen to thirty-five.
Whatever.
Twenty years time.
Enough time.
You can do it in
a much shorter period of time.
Like I did, if you want to.
But this is a reasonable enough time.
But here's number one.
First of all, you've got to have the right philosophy.
Philosophy is our ability to gather knowledge
and sort through it and decide what's valuable.
To develop a philosophy about life.
A philosophy about our health.
A philosophy about our family relationships.
A philosophy about economics.
And if you develop the right philosophy,
that's what helps to set this sail.
So that in six years it
takes you where you want to go.
Instead of winding up like I did
that first six years of my economics.
Broke.
No money.
Empty bank account.
The right philosophy.
Now let me give you
a couple of philosophies to consider.
Here's the first one.
It's called the philosophy of the poor.
And here it is.
Poor people usually spend their
money and invest what's left.
That's the philosophy.
That's the philosophy of the poor.
Now here's the philosophy of the rich.
Rich people invest their money and spend what's left.
And here's the startling answer.
It really doesn't matter what the amount is.
What's most important is not the amount.
What's really important is the philosophy.
So I would ask you to adopt this philosophy.
Of spending after you have invested.
Invest first, then spend.
And I've got a little formula
that I'm going to share with you.
Now what should a child do with a dollar?
I mean there's a lot of debate going on I'm sure
across the country on what a child should do with a dollar.
Here's one opinion.
It's only a child and it's only a dollar.
What difference does it make?
Well, in my opinion it makes
all the difference in the world.
A person's economic future starts
with a child with a dollar.
Somebody says, oh no, you're only young once.
Let him spend it all.
Well, when would you hope that would stop?
Somebody says, well, wait till he's 50
and broke like me and then he'll learn.
Well, no, we don't want to wait that long.
If I would have known earlier
than age 25, I would have changed.
In high school, if they would have had classes
called Wealth 1, Wealth 2, I'd have taken both classes.
I would not have waited until age 25.
So, the earlier the better.
So, what should a child do with a dollar?
Here's the simple premise to begin with.
Don't spend it all.
And if a child wants to spend the whole
dollar, you got to say, hey, don't spend it all.
You know, don't spend it all.
They'll say, why not?
It's my dollar.
I earned it.
You say, I know you earned
it, but don't spend it all.
They'll still say, why not?
Say, let me show you why not.
So, you put them in your car, take them to the other side
of town and show them where people live that spend the whole dollar.
Just drive them around.
Kids learn best by visual.
Just drive around and say,
would you like to live here?
Kid says, no.
Would you like to live like these people live?
Kid says, no, no.
Then you can't spend the whole dollar.
So, kids will get the message.
So, you know, take them to the other side of town and show
them around, unless you already live there, and then just show them around.
Anyway, don't spend the whole dollar.
Now, let me give you my best
view of what to do with a dollar.
And I promise you, if you started at age 15, now,
if you're over 15, right, you've still got to be a dollar.
Right?
You've still got plenty of time.
You've still got 20 years.
You know, if you're 30, you've still got 20 years.
I mean, you know, you've still got plenty of
time to start what I'm about to share with you.
What to do with a dollar.
Here's my first bit of advice.
Never spend more than 70 cents.
Now, you've got to pick some number, and the number
you pick is going to be determined by your philosophy.
It's going to be determined by what
you've been taught or your experience teaching yourself.
When I first met my teacher, Mr. Shouf,
I was at about 110% of each dollar.
You know, I'm down at budget finance, hawking
my furniture and my car one more time.
And then I learned a
whole better formula for financial independence.
Number one, don't spend more than 70 cents.
Now, kids say to me, well, okay, what
do I do with the other 30 cents?
And here's what I teach them.
Ten cents for charity.
Charity or church or helping
people that can't help themselves.
Ten cents to support worthy projects.
Projects that you feel good about.
Ten cents out of every dollar.
It's called being generous with part
of what you've taken out of society.
Now, in my opinion, nothing teaches us character.
Better than generosity.
No class, no teacher, no book.
Teaches character better than generosity.
And the best time to start
is when the amounts are small.
And I know if kids learn these lessons
well, they'll give a dime out of a dollar.
Help people that can't help themselves.
Support worthy projects.
Or if you belong to a
church, they teach tithe, peace of.
That's very important.
Now, because when the amounts get
larger, sometimes it's a little more difficult.
You know, giving 100,000 out of a million.
Someone says, oh, if I
had a million, I'd give 100,000.
I'm not sure.
That's a lot of money.
So the time to start
is when the amounts are small.
Ten cents out of the dollar.
Okay.
Next ten cents.
I call active capital.
Active capital means do something to make a profit.
Active capital.
Set aside a portion of your income.
Wages are okay.
But I'm telling you.
Wages will make you a living.
Profits will make you a fortune.
So set aside part of your
income as capital called active capital.
Any kind of project you can possibly think of.
You can possibly come up with.
I'm going to write a
new book, I think, for kids.
I think the title is going to
be, of course, kids should pay taxes.
It's kind of an interesting title.
In California, kids do pay taxes.
When a child walks into 7-Eleven,
buys something that costs a dollar,
the proprietor says, give me seven more pennies.
And the child says, hey, what's these seven pennies for?
And the proprietor says, that's the taxes.
Kid says, well, hey, I'm only eight years old.
Proprietor says, congratulations,
you're my youngest taxpayer.
Give me the money.
So in California where I live, kids do pay taxes.
Big question is, should they?
And my book will answer that question.
Of course, kids should pay taxes.
Nothing is for free.
If you want to ride your bicycle
on the sidewalk instead of in the mud,
you got to pay the seven pennies.
Nothing is free.
So we all have to pay.
So, ten cents out of your living, out
of the money you earn, set aside for capital.
Capital to try your best to show a profit.
And in my book, it's going to be
all kinds of ways kids can make money, right?
Two bicycles, one to ride and one to rent.
I mean, you know, it doesn't take long to
figure out some enterprise that will start making a profit.
Then you must jot this
down if you're taking a bicycle.
You must jot this down if you're taking notes.
Profits are better than wages.
One, you can't usually start wages
until you're about 16, 15, 16.
But you can make a profit long
before you're eligible to start earning wages.
And then there's no limit to profits.
And they can double and triple and quadruple.
You know, there's no limit.
It's incredible how fast profits can grow.
So profits are better than wages.
Wages make you a living.
Profits make you a fortune.
Now, the third 10 cents is vitally important.
I call it passive capital.
Capital you let somebody else use.
A financial institution, stocks
and bonds, mutual funds, whatever.
Let someone else use it.
You furnish the money.
They use it to make a profit, but they
pay you for the use of it called interest.
And here's one of the things that
will make you financially independent fairly quickly.
And that's called compound interest.
And this is how you get it.
Letting someone else use a
portion of your money, your substance.
They show the profit.
They pay you interest.
And this passive capital, I'm telling
you, over a sustained period of time,
if you'll develop this little 10, 10,
10 and 70, especially starting at age 15,
I'm telling you, by the time
you're 35, you will be financially independent.
You'll have the ability to live
from the income of your own resources.
And then one more point.
On passive capital.
There's a Bible philosophy.
I'm an amateur on the Bible.
But there's a Bible philosophy that teaches
the borrower is servant to the lender.
And if you want to be in a powerful
position as you grow older, finally, when you become mature,
maybe have your own business, things have
worked out for you for the future.
The position you always want to
be in is the power position.
And that's called the lender.
The lender is the power position.
So if kids learn this,
so if kids learn early enough and then you ask
them what they'd like to be when they grow up,
I'm telling you, once they understand, they'll say, well, one of
the things I want to be is one of those lenders.
That's the power position, not the spender.
No, you'll be pitied the rest of
your life if you just become a spender.
You've got to become a lender.
And I think this is
one of the formulas to follow.
Ten cents out of every dollar.
Let someone else use it.
Be the lender.
Power position.
Then try to show a profit.
Can't we teach our children how to take a dollar, search the
neighborhood, find a broken wagon, pay a dollar for it, bring it home,
you know, clean it up, sand it until it's clean, paint
it red till it shines, straighten out the wheels till they're true,
take it back to the
neighborhood, sell it for five dollars?
Anybody can do that.
Now, does the child deserve four dollars profit?
And the answer is yes.
Society now has a mended wagon.
And that's what America is all about.
Finding something, touching it.
Making it better.
Making a profit.
Taking part of your resources.
Helping people who can't help themselves.
Let someone else use it to make a profit.
Some projects require more capital than one person has.
Exciting.
And then let them pay
you for the use of it.
America's had this philosophy now all these years.
Communism has taught all these years capital belongs in the
hands of the state, not in the hands of the people.
We've been teaching all these years capital
belongs in the hands of the people,
not in the hands of the state.
And we turned out to be right.
Capital in the hands of the kids.
Capital in the hands of the people.
Enterprises that make a profit.
Enterprises that grow.
It's the hope of our future.
So that little simple formula I hope will help you.
Now one more key on
financial independence and that is attitude.
Attitude.
Here's number one.
I used to say I hate to pay my bills.
My teacher straightened me out on that.
He said, let's see Mr. Rohn.
What you hate to do is pay $100 on
an account and reduce your liabilities and increase your assets.
I said, well, no, not if
you look at it that way.
He said, well, it all depends
on how you look at it.
So wouldn't you love to pay your
bills, reduce your liabilities, increase your assets?
You've got to have that kind of attitude.
I found out the same attitude about taxes.
I used to say I hate to pay my taxes.
And Mr. Shove said, well, that's one way to live.
And I said, well, that's the other way.
That's the other way to live.
But don't you understand taxes is how we care
and feed the goose that lays the golden eggs.
Wouldn't you want to do your share?
Someone says, yes, but the goose eats too much.
Probably true.
But hey, we all eat too much.
We all need to go on a diet.
Better a fat goose than no goose.
So I finally became a happy taxpayer.
Now I think taxes are too high, so I'm
working to get taxes lowered for our economic future.
But then whatever they turn out to
be, I gladly pay and do my part.
Because that's what makes the whole system
run, each of us doing our part.
Now, I want these three
subjects to be valuable for you.
I want them to have meaning for you.
I want you someday to be financially independent.
I want you to have the personal
development so that you feel good about yourself.
If I had a chance to meet you someday, I'd like to have you show me the
list of goals that you got started and say, Mr. Rohn, here's some I've already checked off.
Here's the books I'm reading.
Here's what's happened.
I'm developing the skills.
I'm better this year than I was last year.
I've got more self-confidence.
My skills are developing.
That's what I want for you.
And that's why I took the time to
come and share in this video message with you.
I do seminars all around the world.
But this is one way that I can reach out and touch
you in case you can't come to my seminars wherever I am.
Maybe this video will reach you somewhere
and it'll have an impact on your life.
And what I'd like to do is,
I'd like to help you to create a website that you can use later, hear
about it, a letter, phone call, or to have a chance to meet you in person.
And now I'd like to leave you
with these four questions called Questions to Ponder.
These questions were valuable for me.
And I want to make them valuable for you.
Here's the first one.
Why?
We all ask why we should work this hard.
Why take that many classes?
Why go to school that many years?
You know?
Why read books?
Why work that hard?
Why put yourself through the push-ups and the disciplines?
Why?
Good question, why?
Best answer to why, I think, is the second question.
Why not?
Why not see how many books you can read, how
many classes you can take, how many skills you can develop?
Why not see how valuable you can become to
the marketplace and to your friends and to your family?
Why not see what you can make of yourself?
Why not see how far you
can go, how much you can see,
how much you can earn, how much you can share?
Why not?
That's the heritage all of us have.
In America especially, is to see what
we can make out of our lives
now that we've been given this extraordinary opportunity.
Now my third question I'd
love to ask you in person.
But since I can't do it in person,
I want to ask it of all of you.
But I want you to take it personally.
And my third question is, why not you?
Why not you?
With good self-esteem.
Why not you starting to change and setting goals?
Why not you starting to
make progress toward financial independence?
If I can do it, you can do it.
I wish I had a lot
more testimonials here today besides mine.
A whole steady stream that would
come by and tell you their story.
Someone who started with nothing,
finally run a big enterprise.
A mother who was on welfare,
now she owns her own business.
In addition to my story, I
wish I had a lot more.
And if I had a lot more,
I wish I had a lot more.
And if all of them told their story,
guess how they would probably wind up their story.
They'd probably say just like me, why not you?
If we can read, you can read.
If we can change, you can change.
If we can figure it
out, you can figure it out.
If we can turn it
around, you can turn it around.
There isn't anything you can't accomplish.
That's what those testimonials would say.
And so I want to say it to you personally.
Why not you?
You've got the brains.
You've got the stamina.
You've got the vitality.
You've got the interest.
You've got your life ahead of you.
You've got the future.
You can do it.
If anybody can do it, you can do it.
If one of us can do
it, hey, we all can do it.
And now here's my last question.
Why not now?
This is a good time as the 20th century starts to wind
down a few more years as we get ready for century 21.
What a good time to set your
goals, work on yourself, work on your skills.
What a good time to get it together.
What a good time to start this process.
Personal development, growing, changing, developing, having a good plan for
your money and for your life and for your future.
Why not now?
And I hope I have a chance to see you one of these days and share
with you the experience, the reaction, the response you might have had from my message today.
And until I get a chance to see you on this side of the world or the other side of the world in some school
or some seminar, or maybe I'll come and speak for a company that you work for someday, I hope I get a chance to meet you.
Until then, I wish you the best.
I want all that I've gotten
to be yours and much, much more.
God bless.
Goodbye.